treating Parkinson's disease with velvet
beans I have several videos on foods
that may trigger Parkinson disease but
how can diet be used in treatment this
video in the next look at beans for
treating this
[Music]
disease two centuries have passed since
James Parkinson's essay on the shaking
py described a disease characterized by
Tremor and problems with movement today
treatment options include surgically
implanting electrodes into the brain
there has to be a better
way we've known since the 1950s that
Parkinson's disease is manifested by a
dopamine deficiency in the brain well
then why not eat a dopamine diet a
variety of fruits and vegetables contain
the same dopamine made by our brain
unfortunately dopamine can't ch the
bloodb brain barrier and hence is
ineffective as therapy however the
dopamine precursor known as lopa or
levadopa can get from the blood up into
the brain where can then be converted to
dopamine within the brain by an enzyme
called
decarboxylase we don't want the levodopa
to be converted to dopamine outside the
brain because then it can't get in so we
give people a decarbox inhibitor which
itself can't get into the brain so that
keeps levodopa from prematurely turning
into dopamine before it gets into the
brain where we need it so eating
dopamine rich foods doesn't help but
what if we ate lopar rich foods more
than 1500 years before Dr Parkinson came
on the scene an Indian physician seemed
to have nailed it and even suggested a
treatment velvet beans the plant with
the highest amount of
elopa huh so might there be a way to
Forstall the epidemic of Parkinson's
disease through plant-based remedies
after all levodopa the gold standard
therapy for Parkinson's patients but
most Parkinson's patients and lowincome
areas cannot afford long-term daily
levodopa therapy in rural Africa for
example it's estimated that only 15% of
patients are treated with levodopa
because the daily cost of levadopa
treatment is about a dollar a day which
may be half of what people make in a day
same with other regions in the global
South l dope is mostly unavailable or
unaffordable so patients frequently use
powdered velvet beans as a replacement
or supplement to the drug but does it
work you never know until you put it to
the test velvet beans in Parkinson's
disease are randomized double blind
clinical study and a dose of 30 gram
which is about 3 tablespoons led to a
reliable and sustained anti-parkinsonian
effect in all patients working
significant L quicker than the drug
working significantly longer than the
drug and working significantly better
than the drug and another doubleblind
randomized head-to-head crossover study
the leop and velvet beans appears to be
two to three times more potent as
compared to the same dose of pill form
levodopa suspected to be because there
may be some intrinsic decarboxylase
inhibitor compound in the plant as well
okay but those were single dose studies
what about The Chronic use of velvet
beans for Parkinson's 14 patients with
Advanced Parkinson's received roasted
velvet bean powder or the standard drug
switching back and forth for months
looking at changes in quality of life
activities of daily living movement and
non-movement symptoms and time with good
Mobility without Troublesome involuntary
writhing movements and the Velvet beans
seem to work as well as to drug in all
measures of efficacy including quality
of life here's a video of someone with
Parkinson been solely treated with
velvet bean powder for 14 years before
and after treatment okay so can you put
both hands out for
me and tap your fingers on the right
just the right try to go
big and the
left and turn
[Music]
the
left the
right turn turn around
see I'm
learning despite the efficacy the
chances of this cheap herbal remedy ever
being licensed seems unlikely and for
good reason first of all this stuff
evidently tastes nasty and we don't
really have good data going out more
than a few months while velvet beans May
potentially be part of the answer to
Parkinson's disease management in
low-income countries and High income
countries one may be tempted to prefer
them to drugs just because it's a more
natural therapy but researchers
discourage patients and Physicians to
consider its use when the drugs are
available so leave it open pill form
should remain the first line treatment
for Parkinson's however velvet bean
powder may be better tolerated in
certain patients psychologically some
patients just have a thing against
taking pills and so if they refuse then
certainly the beans can step in but
otherwise velvet bean supplements suffer
from the same issues common to all
supplements specifically lack of
sufficient regulation and quality
control there's all sorts of Brands out
there but there's no head-to-head
comparisons as to which is best and the
quality of the products likely vary but
you don't know until you put it to the
test six brands of velvet beam product
were ordered through the internet and
most of them four out of six showed a
large discrepancy between the claim on
their label and the actual ual elopa
content and only two even came close the
remaining products contain considerably
less less than 10% two cases too bad
there isn't a food source of elopa that
you could just eat instead of taking in
a supplement well wait a second elopa
was originally discovered more than a
century ago in fava beans might eating
faba beans help with Parkinson's I'll
explore just that question next
[Music]